<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Davids deliverance and thanksgiving. A sermon preached before the King at VVhitehall upon June 28. 1660. being the day of solemn thanksgiving for the happy return of His Majesty. By Gilbert Sheldon, D.D. and Dean of His Majesties Chappell Royall. Published by His Majesties speciall command.</title>
            <author>Sheldon, Gilbert, 1598-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1035_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1035[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Davids deliverance and thanksgiving. A sermon preached before the King at VVhitehall upon June 28. 1660. being the day of solemn thanksgiving for the happy return of His Majesty. By Gilbert Sheldon, D.D. and Dean of His Majesties Chappell Royall. Published by His Majesties speciall command.</title>
                  <author>Sheldon, Gilbert, 1598-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Timothy Garthwait, at the little north door of S. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115685:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DAVIDS</hi> Deliverance and Thanksgiving.</p>
            <p>A
SERMON
Preached before the
KING at VVHITEHALL
Upon <hi>June</hi> 28. 1660.</p>
            <p>Being the DAY of
<hi>SOLEMN THANKSGIVING</hi>
FOR THE
Happy RETURN of His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>BY
GILBERT SHELDON, D. D.
AND
Dean of His MAJESTIES Chappell Royall.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Speciall Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Timothy Garthwait,</hi> at the Little North
Door of S. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:115685:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115685:2"/>
            <bibl>PSALM. 18. 49.</bibl>
            <q>Therefore will I give thanks unto thee
(O Lord) among the heathen, and
ſing praiſes unto thy Name.</q>
            <p>The words before run thus.</p>
            <p>Verſ.
<q>46. The Lord liveth, and bleſſed be my rock, and let the God of
my ſalvation be exalted.</q>
               <q>47. It is God that avengeth me, and ſubdueth the people under
me.</q>
               <q>48. He delivereth me from mine enemies, yea thou lifteſt me up
above thoſe that riſe up againſt me; thou haſt delivered me
from the violent man.</q>
               <q>49. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="sermon">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat the Argument of this Pſalm
is; why, when, and by whom
written, the Title ſhews, and tels
us, that 'twas <hi>Davids,</hi> made <hi>in the
day that the Lord delivered him from
all his enemies, and from the hand of
Saul.</hi> 'Tis recorded 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. after the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Sheba,</hi> and 'tis thought by ſome
to be one of the laſt, if not the very laſt, that ever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115685:3"/>
he made. I ſhall not meddle at all with the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi>
or <hi>Prophetical</hi> ſenſe of it, either as it relates to
Chriſt or his Church, matters more proper for
other times; but onely with the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> or <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi>
as it concerned <hi>David,</hi> and by his example all
that ſucceed him in the like Dangers and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances;
even us at preſent, and proper and fit it
is for us. For 'tis a <hi>Pſalm of Thankſgiving</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
and the Verſes read unto you are a ſum of the
whole, a recapitulation of all that went before,
where after a <hi>Commemoration</hi> of Gods ſeveral <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances,</hi>
he infers his own Duty, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
ours, in the words of the Text: Becauſe
thou haſt ſo graciouſly, ſo mercifully delivered me
from ſo many and great dangers,
<q>Therefore will I give thanks unto thee (O Lord)
among the Heathen, and ſing praiſes unto thy
Name.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein be pleaſed to take notice with me of
theſe three particulars.
<list>
                     <item>1. Of David delivered.</item>
                     <item>2. Of God his Deliverer.</item>
                     <item>3. Of Davids thankfulneſſe for his deliverance.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe in order; and firſt, of the perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115685:3"/>
I. <hi>DAvid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. David delivered.</note> a <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Saint,</hi> both which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title
him to an eſpecial intereſt in
Gods good Providence: <hi>Kings</hi> are his
<hi>Deputies, Saints</hi> his <hi>Friends;</hi> and <hi>David</hi> no ordinary
<hi>King</hi> or <hi>Saint,</hi> but eminent in both relations; an
excellent Perſon,<note place="margin">Act. 13. 22.</note> and gracious <hi>King,</hi> one <hi>after Gods
own heart,</hi> a Type of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and no marvel if ſuch be
delivered by him, if God have an eſpecial care of
him. The <hi>wonder</hi> is, how ſo good a Man, ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
a Prince, ſhould have Enemies and Rebels,
ſhould fall into ſuch dangers and afflictions,
ſhould need ſo many deliverances.</p>
                  <p>But if we conſider it well, it's no wonder nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
never was, never will be: For if we look
to the eminenteſt perſons in all Ages of the World,
from the firſt man to this day, we ſhall find
that the beſt of Men and moſt godly, have
ever had many afflictions, many enemies, and
many the more for being ſo. The <hi>Prophet</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains
'twas his caſe, and that he ſuffered much <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he followed the thing that good was,</hi> Pſal. 38. 20.
And St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, that <hi>All</hi> (all without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception)
<hi>that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
perſecution,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 12. and if there were no
other cauſe, even for their <hi>godlineſſe:</hi> their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
are a reproach to the wicked world, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
well be endured.</p>
                  <p>But reaſon enough for it there is beſides; for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115685:4"/>
even in the <hi>beſt,</hi> there is ſomething <hi>amiſſe;</hi> no corn
without chaff, nor gold without ſome droſs: All
Saints are ſinners, and ſin will be puniſhed in
Gods children ſooneſt of all, he leaſt endures it
in them:<note place="margin">Pſa. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14.</note> 'Tis the wicked uſually that have <hi>their
portion in this life,</hi> and that come <hi>in no trouble like
other men, Pſal.</hi> 73 5. Proſperity in ſin is their
curſe, a ſad ſign of utter deſtruction, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
next ſtep to Hell fire: But they who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
for Heaven, muſt paſs thither <hi>through much
tribulation, Act.</hi> 14. 22. There is ever an <hi>Aegypt</hi> in
their way to <hi>Canaan.</hi> Only this is their comfort,
that being under his <hi>Rod,</hi> they are not out of his
<hi>Care:</hi> Afflictions are their Phyſick; and by
them,<note place="margin">Prov. 27. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>like Gold in the Furnace,</hi> they gain luſtre, and
loſe no weight, are mended here that they may
be ſaved hereafter. No marvel then if a <hi>Saint</hi> fall
into trouble, if he need deliverance; eſpecially
if a <hi>King,</hi> if a <hi>Saint-Royal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For no ſtate or condition of men in the world
is ſo obnoxious to dangers as theirs: For man by
nature is proud and querulous, impatient of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
greedy of liberty, ever reſtleſs and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
after new deſires, always diſpleaſed with the
preſent, and thirſting after change; ſcarce any
content with their condition. Some are <hi>ambitious</hi>
and would be greater; others <hi>covetous</hi> and would
be richer; have ſuffered a repulſe in ſome unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
ſuits, have been reſtrained in ſome exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115685:4"/>
deſires; injuries not to be forgiven or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.
Some are <hi>neceſſitous,</hi> and ſo greedy; ſome
<hi>revengeful,</hi> and will be quarrelling; ſome <hi>envious,</hi>
ſome <hi>turbulent,</hi> and delight in miſchief, and many
the like. Now all this crowd and throng of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
paſſions and humors diſchargeth it ſelf
upon thoſe in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> and hope to find
eaſe by ſome publick diſturbance, which they
endeavour by all arts and wayes imaginable, that
ſo in troubled waters they may catch that which
quieter times would have derived upon perſons of
better merit.</p>
                  <p>And the condition of <hi>Kings</hi> gives ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
to ſuch deſigns; for they ſtand high, all eyes
are upon them, nothing they ſay or do eſcapes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
and cenſure; if any thing be amiſs (as
in the diſtraction of many cares, and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
of much buſineſs, 'tis impoſſible but that ſome
ſlips ſhould happen, ſome errors be committed)
they are ſure to hear of them to their greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage:
a <hi>Mote</hi> will be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> called a <hi>Beam,</hi> a <hi>Gnat</hi>
a <hi>Camel;</hi> and a few will be multiplied into
many.</p>
                  <p>'Twere happy with the world, were every man
as <hi>wiſe</hi> as he thinks himſelf; but the <hi>opinion of
Wiſdome</hi> is the greateſt part of <hi>Folly,</hi> and that the
common diſeaſe of Mankind: And ſo much the
worſe, becauſe they ever think themſelves wiſeſt
in other mens buſineſs, are ever complaining
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115685:5"/>
they do not their duty, eſpecially <hi>Governours,</hi> whoſe
great misfortune it is, that if all be well with us
by their care and wiſdom, we thank our ſelves
for it; if any thing amiſs, we blame them; and
what fals upon us by our own <hi>ſins,</hi> we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
with great injuſtice impute to their <hi>errors.</hi>
And which is ſtill worſe, if they cannot be juſtly
charged with any miſcarriage, yet that helps not:
Innocency is no protection for them; their place
and power is crime enough to pull them down,
others would be where they are, who like the
Devil (as St. <hi>Bernard) Malunt miſerè praeeſſe, quam
feliciter ſubeſſe;</hi> had rather be miſerable in power,
then happy in ſubjection; and then to make
way for their ambition, faults muſt be found,
though there be none; and 'tis ſtrange how far
impudent <hi>calumnies</hi> prevail with a diſcontented
people, and gain belief beyond all imagination,
ever againſt ſenſe and reaſon.</p>
                  <p>And therefore if you look upon the beſt of
PRINCES in prophane Stories,<note place="margin">The beſt of Princes moſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> you ſhall find
them by theſe Arts and wayes exerciſed as much as
any, if not more; by <hi>Mutinies, Seditions, Rebellions:</hi>
I forbear inſtances very obvious, and ſhall onely
touch upon ſome we find regiſtred in Scripture.
And firſt upon <hi>David</hi> in the Text.</p>
                  <p>A vertuous and pious man,<note place="margin">DAVID.</note> a great Souldier, a
gracious Prince, one that wanted nothing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
a people to obedience and reſpect, <hi>a man after
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115685:5"/>
Gods own heart, 1 Sam.</hi> 13. 14. propoſed as a pattern
to <hi>Solomon,</hi> with a promiſe to entail his Kingdome
and bleſſing upon him and his poſterity, if he
would <hi>but walk in his ſteps, 2 Chron. 7. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 18. the
meaſure and ſtandard by which the ſucceeding
Princes were judged <hi>His heart was not perfect, as
my ſervant Davids;</hi> ſo of many: Or, he did <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to all that my ſervant David did;</hi> ſo of others, and
that was thought commendations enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> His
Vertues out-lived himſelf, and many generations
fared the better for him; <hi>Solomon</hi> the Father, and
<hi>Rehoboam</hi> the Son, and many more preſerved from
utter ruine for his ſake. And in the days of <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>
(above Three hundred years after) <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
her ſelf in greateſt diſtreſs, defended by God, for
his <hi>own ſake, and for his ſervant Davids ſake. 2 Kings</hi>
19. 34.</p>
                  <p>Yet this rare and excellent perſon, this gracious
Prince, the very <hi>light of Iſrael,</hi> as his Subjects ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 17. was reſtleſs all his
days; I cannot reckon his <hi>troubles,</hi> becauſe he
himſelf ſays they were <hi>innumerable, Pſal.</hi> 40. 12.
nor his enemies that <hi>hated him without cauſe,</hi> and
ſought to <hi>deſtroy him wrongfully,</hi> for <hi>they were mighty,
Pſal.</hi> 38. 19. and <hi>more then the hairs of his head, Pſal.</hi>
69. 4. and that of all ſorts, from the graveſt that
<hi>ſate in the Gates,</hi> (the place of Judicature) <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.
down to the <hi>Drunkards</hi> and very ſcum of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
the one <hi>made ſongs,</hi> the other put ſcorns <hi>upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115685:6"/>
him, Pſal.</hi> 35. 15. ſlandered his <hi>Perſon,</hi> traduced
his <hi>Government,</hi> which God himſelf never found
fault with; and at laſt took Arms againſt him,
drove him from his <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Imperial City,</hi> forced
him to flee he knew not whither, glad to take any
way for preſent ſafety: And to make up his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows
to the full, who ſhould head theſe Rebels
but his dearly beloved <hi>Abſolom!</hi> who drew into
conſpiracy with him, beſides the moſt of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
even his own <hi>familiar friends whom he truſted,
which did alſo eat of his bread;</hi> ſuch as he had moſt
obliged, his very Favourites, as he complained
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 9. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 13. where he bemoans
his own preſent diſtreſs, and the perfidiouſneſs of
his own principal Servants and Councellors, who,
with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> ſought his Life and Crown: Nay,
they ſuffered him not to die in peace; for <hi>Adonijah,</hi>
another of his darling Sons, obtrudes himſelf a
Succeſſor upon him, without his conſent or
knowledge, and as it were to bury him alive.
1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 1. 5, 6.</p>
                  <p>Thus was this excellent <hi>King</hi> uſed.<note place="margin">SOLOMON</note> And though
he left behind him a Succeſſor, a glorious type of
Chriſt, <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt King that ever was, or
ever will be; yet he fared little better. He was
himſelf the <hi>wonder,</hi> and made his people the <hi>envy</hi>
of the world, by the affluence of all temporal
bleſſings; they had <hi>Silver and Gold as ſtones, 2 Chro.</hi>
1. 15. they were multiplied as the <hi>ſand of the ſea,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115685:6"/>
eating and drinking, and making merry, 1 Kin.</hi> 4. 20.
a ſtate of life one would think that no diſcontent
could lodge with. But <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>plenty,</hi> which
are thought to make men <hi>happy,</hi> cannot always
make them <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>content;</hi> nor can any benefits
though never ſo great, ſtop the mouth of ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
and impatience. While all the world
thought them the happieſt people under the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
they murmur and complain at I know not
what imaginary <hi>burdens,</hi> which they call <hi>heavy,</hi>
and a <hi>greivous Yoke, 1 Kin.</hi> 12. 4. and ſo little to
be endured, that they were ready to break out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Rebellion againſt him, had not God's mercy
and his mercy prevented it, even in his time:
And he no ſooner dead, but ten tribes, for that
reaſon, caſt off the Government of his ſon, with
what ſucceſs we all know.</p>
                  <p>But theſe two, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> had their
faults, and great ones too, for which they were
puniſhed! 'Tis true, they had ſo; but none to
provoke their people to diſobedience; they were
private and Perſonall, not of publick concernment;
their Government was juſt and moderate, never
taxed by God as their faults were; and if this
muſt be aſſigned a juſt cauſe of diſturbance, that
they were <hi>Governed by Men</hi> not by <hi>Angels,</hi> by thoſe
ſubject to humane infirmities like themſelves, all
the world will be in a combuſtion, and none left
to govern in peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115685:7"/>
But what ſay you then (in the laſt place) to
Innocency it ſelf, one againſt whom nothing
could be juſtly objected,<note place="margin">Moſes.</note> either as a private or
publick perſon? ſure he muſt needs eſcape the
malice and machinations of all male contents!
No, he did not; his condition as bad as any.
'Twas <hi>Moſes</hi> I mean; ſo rare a perſon, that (as
St. <hi>Ambroſe) he blotted out all that was man in him
by the purity of a converſation wholly celeſtiall.</hi>
And <hi>Joſephus</hi> tels us, <hi>that his affections were ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
by wiſdome, that he ſeemed utterly to want
them, &amp; that he knew only the names of thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
which he perceived to be too active in other men.</hi>
Moſt certain it is, that he was an excellent <hi>perſon</hi>
in himſelf, and an excellent <hi>Governor</hi> to them: I
cannot inſiſt upon his particular Vertues in either
kind; ſure I am, he wanted none that might oblige
his people to obedience. Yet, beſides and above all,
what a ſeries of <hi>Miracles</hi> were wrought by God, to
give him authority and credit among the people?
And ſure all this might have been ſufficient to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
his quiet in a Government ſo poor and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and ſuch as was impoſſible for any elſe
to manage without the ſame miraculous aſſiſtance
of God.</p>
                  <p>And yet all this could not do it; for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
all theſe advantages, what a weariſom life
did he lead in a continuall ſucceſſion of <hi>murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
mutinies, conſpiracies, rebellions</hi> of perſons
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115685:7"/>
neither few nor mean, and ſome of his <hi>own blood?</hi>
How many faults do they charge him with? <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
miſgovernment,</hi> a deſign to bring the people
out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> to periſh in the Wilderneſs, as if
there <hi>wanted graves there,</hi> and theſe reproaches of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
repeated: And with a wonderfull ſtrange im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence
they call him <hi>Tyrant,</hi> a <hi>killer of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
for what's that elſe? And this more then
once or twice, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. and <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. And
though God choſe him to that command for his
very <hi>Meekneſſe, Ecclus</hi> 45. 4. and he was indeed
the <hi>meekeſt man upon the face of the earth Num. 12
3.</hi> yet he is traduced by them as a <hi>Killer of God's
people,</hi> as <hi>a Tyrant;</hi> ſuch is the juſtice of Rebels. It
cannot then be thought ſtrange that any after him
ſhould ſuffer under the like calumny that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
it as little: For if any way faulty, 'twas in
too much Lenity.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee how impoſſible it is for Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
to eſcape theſe ſcourges, whether they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
them or no, whether inocent or guilty. For
if <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>meekeſt, David</hi> the <hi>beſt, Solomon the
wiſeſt</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> felt the ſmart of popular murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
tumults and rebellions; perſons as excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
as ever the world had any, or ever will have;
if they could not eſcape, what good Prince ſhould
forfeit his patience by it? think it ſtrange, or be
diſcouraged at it? Or how dare any miſ-judge
or cenſure them for it, as if forſaken of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115685:8"/>
abuſed by men? or deſigned for utter ruine,
becauſe under his fatherly correction. Conſider
who theſe were, what they did, and what they
ſuffered, and then let him that dare pronounce
amiſſe of any in their caſe and condition.</p>
                  <p>'Tis clear then by what has been ſaid, that the
<hi>beſt of Kings</hi> may be <hi>under the Croſs,</hi> as much as
any, and more than any have been, and certainly
wil be ſo to the world's end; and ſo will, as much
as any, need <hi>deliverance,</hi> &amp; ſhal undoubtedly have
it, they eſpecially, they before and above others.
For they are <hi>God's peculiar care,</hi> they are his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi>
his <hi>Deputies,</hi> his honor is concerned in them,
and the preſervation of them is the good of many;
<hi>Thou art worth ten thouſand of us,</hi> ſay <hi>David's</hi>
Subjects to him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 3.</p>
                  <p>But though <hi>delivered</hi> they ſhall be, and ever will
be, yet 'tis not always at the ſame time; ſome conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
longer under the Croſs, ſome are eaſed ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:
Nor in the ſame manner and way; ſome he
preſerves and ſupports <hi>in danger,</hi> and at laſt gives
them ſafety and peace; others he delivers <hi>from
danger,</hi> by taking them to himſelf. The firſt was
the Deliverance of the <hi>three Children,</hi> when they
came untouch'd out of the fire; the ſecond of the
<hi>Maccabees,</hi> and thouſands more, whom by a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<hi>Martyrdom</hi> he took to himſelf. Great Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances
both, but that of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> much the
greater, much the better; when from a fading
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115685:8"/>
Crown, a Scepter clouded with cares, and a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome
Life ever tending to Death, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
up to a Crown of Glory, and a Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
in the Heavens. He that looks not on this as
the better of the two, deſerves neither; and one of
the two they, and all his Servants, may be ſure of.
So that let <hi>the troubles of the righteous be many &amp;
great,</hi> as indeed <hi>many and great</hi> they uſually are, yet
firſt or laſt, one way or other, and ever to his beſt
advantage, <hi>the Lord delivers him out of all, Pſal.</hi>
34. 18. And ſo I paſs from the <hi>Perſon</hi> here <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,</hi>
to the <hi>Lord that delivered him,</hi> the ſecond
thing propoſed to your conſideration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <p>II. THat <hi>all Deliverance comes from</hi> (him,<note place="margin">2. God the Deliverer.</note>
from) <hi>the Lord,</hi> 'twere needleſs to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
Proofs out of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which are but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters
of his <hi>Providence,</hi> and you cannot look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
them there. And 'tis no leſſe apparent unto
<hi>Reaſon;</hi> for that <hi>(with great clearneſs, and by a
degree of evidence even beyond knowledge,</hi> as thoſe
old Philoſophers <hi>Hermes</hi> and <hi>Jamblicus</hi> expreſs it)
finds that <hi>there is a God,</hi> and from thence (with
as great evidence) demonſtrates a <hi>Providence.</hi> So
that ſhould I lead you out of the <hi>Church</hi> into the
<hi>Schools</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers, Poets, Historians,</hi> Writers
of all ſorts among the Heathens, you would finde
them, by the very inſtinct and impreſſion of
Nature, acknowledging the ſame truth; ever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115685:9"/>
aſcribing all good ſucceſſes to their <hi>Gods,</hi> and
accordingly giving thanks, offering ſacrifices, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting
Feaſts and Holy-dayes, putting Garlands
upon their Images, leaving part of their ſpoils ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in their Temples: A Truth ſo viſible, that
even blind Nature ſaw it.</p>
                  <p>But to our great ſhame and greater grief be it
ſpoken,<note place="margin">His parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> we have ſome among us (I hear many)
more heatheniſh than the Heathen, that will not
allow <hi>God</hi> to govern in his own Houſe, that deny
him any <hi>care of things below;</hi> ſo far from deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
us out of danger, that he neither regards how
we come in, or how we get out, nor at all looks
after any thing elſe we are concern'd in. A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion
extreamly croſs to the <hi>common notions</hi> of
mankind, and impreſſions of <hi>Nature,</hi> that wholly
makes void and ridiculous the duty we are about,
and indeed all other; for 'tis totally <hi>deſtructive</hi> of
all <hi>Vertue, Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> none of which
can poſſibly ſubſiſt, without a belief, a ſenſe, a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
of ſome <hi>Divine Power</hi> that will be ſure to
call for an account of whatſoever we do. Yet they
ſay, theſe are the <hi>great Wits</hi> of the time, the onely
men of parts among us. I wonder at it; 'twas not
ſo thought of old; the language of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
imports not any great eſteem of them; Nay,
he is ſo far from it, that he wonders at their <hi>ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:
O ye bruitiſh among the people, &amp; ye fools, when
wil ye be wiſe? Pſ.</hi> 94. 8. He ſpeaks of ſuch as when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115685:9"/>
they do wickedly, ſay; <hi>Tuſh, the Lord ſhall not ſee,
neither ſhal the God of Jacob regard it, v.</hi> 7. He wil
neither <hi>take notice,</hi> nor <hi>puniſh,</hi> he looks after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
here below, we may do what we pleaſe for
him. Now let who will admire them, yet theſe are
the men he cals <hi>bruits</hi> and <hi>fools,</hi> and he doth it
not once or twice, but very oft. <hi>The fool hath ſaid in
his heart, There is no God, Pſ.</hi> 14. 1. that is, no <hi>Judge,</hi>
no <hi>Providence,</hi> (as the word there ſignifies.) And
again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53. 1. and oft elſewhere, if not in the
ſame words, yet to the ſame ſenſe and purpoſe. I
hope you will not think the term uncivil, 'tis not
mine, but <hi>David's.</hi> And if you doubt whether
they deſerve it, you ſhall have it from a <hi>wiſer</hi> than
he, &amp; I hope one they will <hi>acknowledge wiſer</hi> than
themſelves too, even from <hi>Solomon,</hi> who being the
wiſeſt of all men, might have the priviledge to be
bold with them, as one that beſt knew what they
were; yet he brings them in wondring at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
of the Righteous, which they believed little
of, and putting upon themſelves that ſcorn and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<hi>We fools counted his life madneſs, Wiſd.</hi> 5. 4.
We thought our ſelves <hi>wiſe</hi> in purſuing pleaſure
without check or reſtraint, and him <hi>mad</hi> for not
doing as we did: but now we finde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (too late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed)
but find it we do, and that to our confuſion
and horror, that his <hi>Madneſs</hi> was <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and
our <hi>Wiſdom folly; We fools</hi> thought ſo, but <hi>Fools</hi>
we were, for ſo thinking. Now what <hi>fools</hi> ſay is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115685:10"/>
little to be regarded; the Sun ſhines though the
blind ſee it not, and <hi>a God</hi> and <hi>Providence</hi> there is
that ſends Deliverance, though the <hi>fool</hi> ſay, There
is not: and ſo let the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> paſſe under <hi>David's</hi>
and <hi>Solomon's</hi> Character, while we to our great
comfort (one of the greateſt we are capable of in
this world) acknowledge, believe, and viſibly ſee,
and by experience find, That there is a good <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi>
over us that orders all the affairs of the
world from the leaſt to the greateſt; from <hi>Empires</hi>
and <hi>Thrones to the falling of a Sparrow on the
ground, and the very numbring of our hairs,</hi> as our
Saviour <hi>S. Math.</hi> 10. 29, 30.</p>
                  <p>That as 'tis He, and He only, that brings us into
danger, that lays afflictions on us for our ſins; (for
<hi>who gave Jacob for a ſpoil, and Iſrael to the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?
did not the Lord, he againſt whom they had
ſinned? For they would not walk in his ways,
neither were they obedient to his Law,</hi> therefore <hi>he
hath powred upon them the fury of his anger, and
the ſtrength of battel,</hi> Iſa. 42. 24, 25. Juſt our
caſe, we ſerved him ſo, he ſerved us ſo; our
great ſins brought his great judgements upon us.
And) ſo againe 'tis He, and He onely, that
muſt remove thoſe afflictions, that muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
out of thoſe dangers: For, <hi>who is
God but the Lord? and who hath any ſtrength</hi> to
doe it <hi>except our God?</hi> 'Tis <hi>David's</hi> queſtion
at ver. 31. of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and our anſwer muſt be,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115685:10"/>
None can do it elſe, none but he: Neither <hi>Men,</hi>
nor <hi>Angels,</hi> nor any nor all the <hi>Creatures</hi> of Heaven
and Earth can give it. They may be <hi>Inſtruments</hi>
in his hand, which he moves, directs, orders, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
and reſtrains, when he will and how he will;
he delivers by them if you will; and he too with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
them when he will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no <hi>Means</hi> too weak with
him, none ſtrong enough without him; but
whether with or without <hi>means,</hi> 'tis ſtill he that
does it, he that delivers, and none elſe; For <hi>the
help that is done upon Earth, he doth it himſelf,</hi>
as 'tis in the Old Tranſlation <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 13.</p>
                  <p>Sure I am,<note place="margin">Application.</note> we found it ſo; all we did, or could
do, toward a ſettlement proved nothing worth, all
attempts vain, no <hi>Treaties,</hi> no <hi>Armies,</hi> no <hi>Endeavors</hi>
by our ſelves or others that wiſhed well to our
Peace did us good, though never ſo probable, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſo hopeful; they were all loſt and fruſtrate, all
vaniſhed into nothing. How viſible was Gods
hand in it, when all raſh and unreaſonable <hi>attempts</hi>
proſpered with ſome, while others failed in the
beſt and moſt probable? And either the <hi>worſt
Counſels</hi> were followed (as it uſually happens
when God determines to judge and afflict a ſinfull
Nation) or the <hi>beſt</hi> never proſpered, but when
brought to ripeneſs miſcarried in the birth. Thus
it conſtantly was, and thus it would have been
till we had been utterly conſumed, had not he
had mercy on us, had he not raiſed up a <hi>Deliverer,</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115685:11"/>
never to be mentioned without Honour, nor to
be forgotten in the <hi>Prayers</hi> of all good People, that
God would multiply his favours and bleſſings,
both temporal and ſpiritual, upon his <hi>Perſon</hi> and
<hi>Poſterity</hi> for many Generations.</p>
                  <p>But whoever were the Inſtruments of our <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance,</hi>
we muſt ſtill remember to raiſe up our
thoughts to him by whoſe power they wrought
it, and give him the glory of all; ſince nothing is
more certain that none did it, none could do it
but he; and having this experience of his power
and goodneſſe, it muſt be a warning to us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,
that we looſe not our labour in ſeeking it elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where;
that we have patience to wait for it till
he is pleaſed to give it; that we ſuffer not our eager
deſires or fears to haſten it, by unlawful means, to
purchaſe it by ſin.</p>
                  <p>VVere we right <hi>in our Faith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">We muſt not do evill that good may come of it.</note> we ſhould think it
impoſſible to be had without him (as indeed it
is, unleſſe he permit it for our greater miſchief; for
who can <hi>reſiſt his will?)</hi> and were we right in
our <hi>Wits,</hi> we ſhould not think it worth the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
but by him; for he that to eſcape <hi>Danger,</hi>
runs into a <hi>ſin,</hi> is much like the ſtarting Horſe, who
to avoid a <hi>ſhadow</hi> upon one ſide the way, leaps
down a <hi>precipice,</hi> to his ruine, on the other, and
like him that for fear of a leſſer, runs into a greater
miſchief: and to avoid a <hi>Pot-gun,</hi> throws himſelf
into the mouth of a <hi>Cannon.</hi> A ſad bargain it is,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115685:11"/>
let the <hi>State-Atheiſt</hi> think what he will, to buy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance
from the greateſt <hi>temporal miſchief,</hi> by the
leaſt <hi>wilfull ſin;</hi> to ſave Wealth, Honour, Crowns
and Scepters, Life it ſelf, any thing we have, or
all, at the loſs of our God, at the expence of our
Soul, which exceeds the whole VVorld in value,
and all it hath in it.</p>
                  <p>But there is a further degree of <hi>Folly</hi> in this
courſe, ſtill a greater blindneſs; for we ſacrifice
the comforts of this Life, and hopes of a better,
(which every wilful known ſin robs us of) for
juſt <hi>nothing:</hi> VVe believe indeed we purchaſe <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi>
by <hi>ſin,</hi> and think we have it, when at the
beſt 'tis but an <hi>exchange</hi> of danger, and that too
the little for the great; ſome trouble here, for
eternal damnation hereafter: Nay 'tis not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways,
not oft ſo much neither, as an <hi>exchange</hi> of
danger, (though that bargain is made ſad enough
by the diſproportion) but a <hi>doubling</hi> of it if you
will; a contracting a new <hi>danger</hi> by a new <hi>ſin,</hi> and
but a running from the old <hi>one way,</hi> to meet it <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other;</hi>
a bringing of what we labour to avoid, with
more ſpeed and greater certainty upon us.</p>
                  <p>VVould you have Reſolution of a <hi>Council</hi> of
<hi>State-Atheiſts</hi> in the caſe, and ſee how it ſped?
You ſhall find it at the <hi>11 chap.</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<hi>verſ. 47. 48. What do we?</hi> (ſay the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and
<hi>Phariſees</hi> ſitting in Council againſt our Saviour)
<hi>for this man doth many miracles, and if we let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115685:12"/>
all men will believe on him, and the Romans ſhall
come and take away both our place and Nation.</hi> What
was reſolved on? what was done upon this? Why,
the fear of this <hi>danger</hi> put them upon a horrid <hi>ſin,</hi>
the ſhedding of moſt innocent blood, they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
him: And did that avoid the danger they
feared by it? No; the <hi>Romans</hi> did come, and for
the puniſhment of that very ſin, <hi>took away their
place,</hi> carried them captive, deſtroyed their <hi>Nation.</hi>
'Tis St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s obſervation, confirmed by the
experience of all Ages.</p>
                  <p>I will not ſay it always happens ſo; a ſpeedy
<hi>Repentance</hi> may ſometimes give a ſtop to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
courſe of Gods <hi>Judgments;</hi> but it very oft,
it moſt commonly happens ſo, as all <hi>Hiſtories</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
and our own <hi>Experience</hi> can tell us, perhaps
in our own particular affairs; in the <hi>Publick</hi>
it hath ever been too too viſible, when <hi>Reaſon</hi> of
<hi>State</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>God, prudence</hi> (falſly ſo called)
and cunning, to <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>honeſty.</hi> For when
we begin once to diſtruſt that God cannot, or will
not <hi>provide</hi> for our ſafety, and fall to ſhift for our
ſelves by ſuch ways as he approves not, we forfeit
our title to his good <hi>providence,</hi> (which one way
or other would moſt certainly ſave us, did we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
upon it) and bring upon our ſelves the ſad
effects of diſtruſt, by <hi>changing</hi> our <hi>probable fears</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<hi>certain ſufferings,</hi> and very oft into the ſame we
run from; for we very ſeldome do wickedly to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115685:12"/>
prevent a miſchief, but that very miſchief falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
us, as a puniſhment for that wickedneſs. A hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
inſtances might be given out of Story, and moſt
mens breaſts would be found Regiſters of this ſad
Truth, would they be pleaſed to ſearch them well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
So clear is that of the <hi>Preacher.</hi> That <hi>wickedneſs ſhall
not deliver thoſe that are given to it. Eccleſ.</hi> 8. 8.</p>
                  <p>And therefore if we do indeed believe this moſt
certain truth, <hi>That all deliverance is from the Lord,</hi>
we muſt ſhew the fruits of that <hi>Faith,</hi> when in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.
And if we cannot by good wayes compaſſe
our ſafety, never ſtrive to do it by ill; but ſubmit,
and expect with <hi>patience</hi> till he is pleaſed to give it:
For then, and not till then, 'twill be a <hi>Deliverance,</hi>
indeed. VVe muſt not run to the Creature for
relief in <hi>dangers but to him;</hi> nor expect <hi>deliverance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
but from Him, nor ſeek <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t but in his way, by him,
and at his time: And when we have it, to be ſure
with <hi>David</hi> to <hi>thank</hi> him for it, to pay our Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
where it is due. And ſo I paſſe to the laſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
propoſed, <hi>Davids thankfulneſſe for his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.
I will give thanks unto thee (O Lord)
among the Heathen, and ſing praiſes unto thy Name.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115685:13"/>
                     <hi>
                        <note place="margin">3. Davids thankfulneſs</note>III. YOu have had the</hi> Perſon delivered, <hi>and</hi>
He that delivered him; <hi>now follows the</hi>
Duty to be performed upon the deliverance: <hi>VVhere
we may obſerve,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The perſon performing it,</hi> that's David: I <hi>will</hi>
do it, ſaith he.</item>
                        <item>2. The Duty it ſelf, <hi>that's</hi> Thanksgiving: I will
give thanks.</item>
                        <item>3. <hi>The Manner how</hi> he will do it, and that
is,</item>
                        <item>1. <hi>Publickly,</hi> diffuſively not only in the
Church, but <hi>among the Heathen</hi> too:</item>
                        <item>2. Cheerfully, I will ſing praiſes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Somthing of each of theſe in the order propoſed.
And firſt of the <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">4. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, [I will.]</note>1. I <hi>will</hi> (ſayes <hi>David,)</hi> and good reaſon he
ſhould, <hi>He</hi> in the firſt place, He to lead the way,
to give the example. The bleſſings were <hi>publick,</hi>
and he a publick <hi>perſon,</hi> ſo more concerned in
them then any other, yet others concerned too
as well as he, though not ſo much, even in thoſe
<hi>Dangers</hi> that aimed only at his <hi>perſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> For that
being of <hi>publick concernment,</hi> his <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances</hi>
could be no leſs: As the <hi>Members</hi> for the
<hi>Head,</hi> hurt that, and all ſuffer with it, even the
loweſt, the meaneſt, the miſchief deſcends to all
and every one, deliver that from danger, and all
rejoyce with it, all the better for it, ſo that if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115685:13"/>
the <hi>King</hi> have cauſe to <hi>give thanks,</hi> if he ſay <hi>I will</hi>
do it, all and every one of his Subjects muſt do
it too.</p>
                  <p>'Tis a great ſhame and folly too, as well as a
great ſin, ſo to mind our private as if we had
no relation to the <hi>publick;</hi> no Obligation to
mourn for, to endeavour to remove <hi>National ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities;</hi>
or to <hi>give thanks</hi> and rejoyce for publick
Mercies and Deliverances, ſince the <hi>publick</hi> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
is each <hi>paticular</hi>'s; for <hi>Quod examini expedit,
idem api;</hi> What's good for the <hi>whole,</hi> is good for
every <hi>part:</hi> And therefore we ſhould be as <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
for <hi>common bleſſings,</hi> as if they were beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
onely upon us; ſince we have our full ſhare in
them, and in our proportion as much as any.
To inſtance in that which moſt concerns us;
<hi>peace</hi> is a collection of all temporal bleſſings, and
that's <hi>Omnium tota &amp; ſingulorum,</hi> every one hath
it as much as any, as much as all: Every one hath
by it a comfortable and quiet enjoyment of all
that belongs to him, every one hath His perſon
and relations ſecured from violence, his fortune
from rapine; and though He have not ſo much
perhaps as others, yet his <hi>All</hi> is as much to him as
all theirs to them; and theſe bleſſings are as full
to thee, as if thou onely enjoyedſt them; and
more to thy <hi>Security,</hi> becauſe others injoy them
with thee. And therefore ſince <hi>every Man</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
in the <hi>Benefit, every man</hi> muſt betake himſelf
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115685:14"/>
to the <hi>Duty;</hi> that's <hi>Thankfulneſs. I will give thanks.</hi>
The next particular.</p>
                  <p>2. And here the time is very obſervable: Our
<hi>Prophet</hi> was no ſooner <hi>delivered,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. [Give thanks.]</note> but he made a
right uſe of that bleſſing, he fell to his Duty of
<hi>Thanks</hi> for it; a thing not ſo uſuall, either with
Kings or meaner perſons. For if any diſturbance
intermit our ſinfull pleaſures, no ſooner that over,
but we return to them again, and with more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs.
<hi>David</hi> will not do it; Now (ſaith he)
I ſee the tempeſt over, the clouds diſperſed, my
troubles at an end, ſhall I wanton it as before? No,
<hi>I will give thanks unto thee, O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this example ſpeaks our duty; for as <hi>he</hi>
did, ſo muſt <hi>we:</hi> In ill we follow <hi>Kings</hi> faſt enough,
tread upon their heels, if not out-go them; their
example works much upon us, too much; why
not in Vertue: why not ſomething at leaſt that
way? In a <hi>duty</hi> ſo neceſſary it ſhould, a Duty
we cannot avoid without great <hi>ſin</hi> as here we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.
For <hi>Gratitude</hi> is an act of <hi>Justice,</hi> the paying
of a debt, and no part of <hi>Juſtice</hi> more neceſſary,
even to preſerve the very frame of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
ſociety,</hi> which ſubſiſt by nothing more, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
elſe, but a mutuall exchange of good offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
take away theſe, the whole world and all in
it muſt periſh: for no Man can live of himſelf, nor
can any thing ſubſiſt of it ſelf, there muſt be a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
gratitude and exchange of offices to preſerve all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115685:14"/>
But the ſubject is infinit, ſhould we take it at
large; we muſt reſtrain it to the preſent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and follow <hi>Davids</hi> ſteps as cloſe as we can;
his caſe was much like ours; we equal'd him in
danger, let's match him in thankfulneſſe; in him
great <hi>bleſſings,</hi> and great <hi>thanks</hi> met well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
we come not behind in <hi>mercy,</hi> let's not
fall ſhort in <hi>gratitude.</hi> Do it we muſt, and do it
to the full we ſhould; that our <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> may
in ſome meaſure (at leaſt as far as our ability will
carry us) anſwer his great <hi>bounty;</hi> ſince, where
much is given, there's not a little required. VVe
have his <hi>promiſe</hi> indeed, for <hi>deliverance</hi> out of
<hi>danger,</hi> but 'tis uſher'd in with one <hi>command</hi> to
<hi>ask</hi> it, and followed with another to be <hi>thankfull
for it, Pſal. 50. 15. Call upon me in the time of
trouble</hi> (there's the command to ask it) <hi>and I will
hear thee,</hi> (there's the promiſed deliverance; for
his hearing is delivering:)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>And thou ſhalt praiſe
me;</hi> there's the duty enjoyned. The two firſt
are paſt with us, God be thanked for it. We
<hi>prayed,</hi> we <hi>asked,</hi> we <hi>called;</hi> he <hi>heared,</hi> he <hi>delivered.</hi>
Now remains our duty, our <hi>praiſe and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſmall Tribute,<note place="margin">The duty eaſie.</note> God knows; a <hi>duty</hi> ſo <hi>eaſie,</hi>
nothing can excuſe us from it. Other duties want
not excuſes, have ſome juſt impediments in ſome
perſons, and at ſome times; as <hi>poverty, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency,
ſickneſs,</hi> or the like; this hath none<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115685:15"/>
have none: All may do it, and at any time; the
rich and the poor, the ſick and the well, the
lame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the ſound: He that wants not an heart,
though he want all things elſe, though a tongue,
may yet <hi>give thanks</hi> and <hi>praiſe; Ipſum voluiſſe,
laudaſſe eſt; non enim verba quaerit, ſed cor,</hi> Aug.
in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134. When all other ways of expreſſing
our thanks fail us, if <hi>ſincerely</hi> and in <hi>earneſt</hi> we
<hi>would</hi> do it, we have done it.<note place="margin">2. Little.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as what he requires is <hi>eaſie,</hi> ſo 'tis <hi>little,</hi>
very little; <hi>little in it ſelf,</hi> what can be leſs then
<hi>Thanks;</hi> but compared with his great mercies,
then this <hi>little</hi> is juſt nothing. The Patriarch <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>
confeſſed to God, that he was <hi>leſs then the
least of his Mercies, Gen.</hi> 32. 10. Yet he a <hi>Gyant</hi> in
vertue and worth, we, the beſt of us, but <hi>Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi>
to him; and if <hi>He</hi> (as great as he was) were
<hi>leſs then the leaſt:</hi> What are <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> to his <hi>great mercies,</hi>
but juſt <hi>nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet ſuch poor wretches we are, 'tis <hi>All</hi> we have
for him, <hi>All</hi> we can return to him; and if he
will have <hi>any thing,</hi> he muſt have this <hi>nothing.</hi>
And ſo gratious he is, that he calls for it, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
it, he is content with this <hi>nothing,</hi> ſuch as
it is: Requires no more from us, then <hi>thanks</hi> and
<hi>praiſe;</hi> and a great vouchſafement it is, that he
will ſuffer us to do it, ſo great and glorious he,
ſo vile and deſpicable we; yet he will have it,
he is pleaſed with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115685:15"/>
But that too for <hi>us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. Profitable to our ſelves.</note> not for <hi>himſelf; we</hi> gain
by it, not <hi>he;</hi> 'tis nothing to <hi>him,</hi> much to <hi>us;</hi> he
is neither the better, if we <hi>thank him,</hi> nor the
worſe, if we <hi>thank him not;</hi> whether we praiſe
or diſpraiſe him, he is ſtill the ſame; but we are
both, better or worſe, as we do it, or neglect it;
tis ever better with us when we do it, worſe
when we do it not. Caſt any thing up toward
Heaven, it falls down upon thee again; ſend up
<hi>thanks</hi> and <hi>praiſe,</hi> and they deſcend in new <hi>favors</hi>
and <hi>bleſſings;</hi> ſend them not up, and look for no
more; <hi>Accipiendis indignus, qui de acceptis ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi>
Bern Nay look to loſe thoſe thou haſt, for be
ſure they will wither and come to nothing;
either they will be <hi>taken away,</hi> or if they ſtay,
they ſhall not miniſter <hi>comfort,</hi> not <hi>that very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi>
which in their own nature they ſeem to
bring; they are not, they ſhall not be <hi>bleſſings</hi> to
thee; the <hi>comfort</hi> is gone, and that's not all; they
turn to <hi>curſes,</hi> become aggravations of <hi>ſin,</hi> addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
to <hi>judgement:</hi> Such a wretched change doth
<hi>unthankfulneſs</hi> make.</p>
                  <p>Do but obſerve how uneaſie ſome men are in
the affluence of all earthly bleſſings, how fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
how diſcontent, how little joy they take
in them? (and <hi>God</hi> grant it be not many a mans
caſe amongſt us, and even in the enjoyment of
our preſent bleſſings,) examine the cauſe, ſearch
the root of this miſchief, and 'twill be found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115685:16"/>
but <hi>Ingratitude</hi> to <hi>God</hi> for them; who though
he leaves the <hi>things</hi> themſelves, yet takes away the
<hi>bleſſing,</hi> the joy, the comfort of them. And who
can ſay, but that a ſlight eſteem, a negligent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment
of his great favors, deſerves all this?</p>
                  <p>Since then this duty of <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>thanks</hi> is ſo
profitable, if we do it; ſo miſchievous, if we do it
not; ſince we are happy, if we do it, (for do that,
and God will do the reſt: Continue to multiply
his <hi>bleſſings</hi> upon us, preſerve what we have, and
give more, even more then we need, more then we
ask;) and on the other ſide we are utterly undone,
if we do it not; for then there is no keeping of what
we have, or if the <hi>thing</hi> ſtay by us, the <hi>bleſſing</hi> of
it will be taken from us, and we ſhall be as miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
in Peace, and much more then we were in war.
And as we cannot <hi>keep</hi> what we <hi>have,</hi> ſo we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<hi>hope</hi> for what we <hi>want:</hi> Our <hi>Ingratitude</hi> hath
ſtopped the paſſage, dryed up the Fountain of
his Mercies towards us, all our hopes are at an
end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the caſe being thus, 'tis moſt neceſſary that
our next enquiry be,</hi> What this duty of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
is, <hi>and</hi> how we may diſcharge our ſelves of it
as we ought,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115685:16"/>
GRATITUDE in its general notion,<note place="margin">Gratitude.</note> is that
vertue, by which we make ſome convenient
or fitting return to another, for ſome free benefit
received from him, and the ſeveral <hi>acts, parts,</hi> or
<hi>duties</hi> of it, are three.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To acknowledge the benefit.</item>
                     <item>2. To thank and praiſe the Benefactor.</item>
                     <item>3. To repay him with the like, or ſome other
kindneſs, as our ability will ſerve, and
opportunity is offered.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>So that 'tis in the <hi>mind</hi> firſt, then in the <hi>mouth,</hi>
both full of <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>thanks;</hi> yet the duty not
full, untill it fill the <hi>hands</hi> too; <hi>conceived</hi> it muſt
be in the <hi>heart, declared</hi> it muſt be by the <hi>tongue,
perfected</hi> it muſt be by the <hi>hand:</hi> And that all
theſe may do their parts, we will a little conſider
them apart,</p>
                  <p>1. And firſt,<note place="margin">1. In the heart.</note> the root of this lies in the <hi>heart,</hi>
the <hi>fountain</hi> of every good action: <hi>Gratitude</hi> muſt
begin there, by an inward acknowledgment and
juſt eſteem of the benefit received; not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
or deny it, is an impudent piece of
<hi>Ingratitude;</hi> to forget it, baſe; and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value
it, comes not far behind either. All theſe
ſins I fear we have much to anſwer for; and ſuch
as brought our late judgments upon us. Now a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115685:17"/>
                     <hi>juſt eſtimate</hi> of what we have received, is a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
againſt all theſe: For if we find that great,
eſpecially in any high meaſure, we cannot for
ſhame, either <hi>deny, undervalue,</hi> or <hi>forget</hi> it; and
therefore, that we may do our duty in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
we are met about, our main, firſt, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
work muſt be, to fix upon our <hi>hearts</hi> a <hi>due
eſteem,</hi> a true ſenſe of the worth and value of the
<hi>great bleſſing</hi> we have lately <hi>received</hi> from <hi>God,</hi>
and are here met to pay our <hi>thanks</hi> for; and the
beſt meaſure of it, is taken from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Of the Giver.</item>
                     <item>2. The benefit it ſelf.</item>
                     <item>3. The manner of giving.</item>
                     <item>4. The time when.</item>
                     <item>5. And the perſons upon whom beſtowed.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>All or any of which uſe either to heighten or
leſſen a benefit received.</p>
                  <p>1. And firſt,<note place="margin">1. A due eſteem of the Giver.</note> the <hi>Giver</hi> commends the gift;
the hand it comes from, adds value to it: A little
favor from a great perſon is ever much eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
a ſmall Donative from a <hi>Prince,</hi> more valued
then greater matters from an <hi>ordinary perſon.</hi> And
there is reaſon for it; for, beſides the <hi>honor</hi> we
get with <hi>others</hi> to be ſo valued by thoſe of high
eſteem, it brings <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> to <hi>our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115685:17"/>
ſelves,</hi> eſpecially in our preſent caſe between
<hi>God</hi> and us, to have ſuch an aſſurance, ſuch an
earneſt of his good will, who is able to do ſo
much for us: It lets us out into new expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of receiving ſtill more and more, from a
bounty ſo great, ſo laſting, ſo boundleſs, ſo end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.
Indeed, <hi>between men</hi> the difference though
much, cannot be ſo much to heighten the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit;
not more then between one piece of earth
and another, the <hi>Mountain</hi> and the <hi>Molchill</hi> at the
moſt; but in the compariſon between <hi>God and
us,</hi> we ſhall be utterly aſtoniſhed, utterly loſt;
that <hi>he</hi> ſo great, ſo glorious, ſo infinite in all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
beyond all we can ſay or think; ſhould
yet vouchſafe to look down upon <hi>us,</hi> to be kind
to <hi>us,</hi> ſo poor, ſo weak, ſo vile, ſo deſpicable
Creatures, even nothing, and worſe then nothing
in compariſon of him. What a condeſcention is
this in him? What an <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> to us?
How much doth it commend any favour, even
the leaſt, to be an earneſt of ſo infinite a bounty?
And therefore in all ſuch caſes our <hi>Gratitude</hi>
muſt not ariſe ſo much from the ſolace that <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
finds in any <hi>bleſſing</hi> beſtowed upon us, as
from the conſideration of the bounty and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of ſo infinite a <hi>Majeſty</hi> towards us.</p>
                  <p>2. Thus you ſee the <hi>Giver</hi> is great,<note place="margin">2. Of the Gift.</note> greater
then all givers elſe put together, great beyond
compare. What is in the next place, the <hi>Gift</hi> it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115685:18"/>
ſelf? That's great too; and though all are ſo
that come from him, yet ſome are greater then
others, and this in its kind as great as any, both in
reſpect of the miſchiefs we are delivered from, and
the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> we receive by it. There's no deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to particulars on either ſide, they are infinite,
eaſie it is to begin to ſpeak of the one, or the other;
the <hi>Miſeries of War,</hi> or the <hi>Bleſſings of Peace:</hi> But
we know not where to end, ſince both are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable;
and the bare names of <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi>
carry to every mans underſtanding a ſummary,
a collection of all temporall <hi>miſchiefs</hi> and <hi>bleſſings.</hi>
And if there be any in Heaven or Hell upon Earth,
theſe are they, and the diſtance as great; however,
they are excellent Hieroglyphicks of both; no two
things in the world reſemble them better.</p>
                  <p>So that if we conſider what we have eſcaped,
the <hi>miſeries of War,</hi> and of a <hi>Civil War,</hi> the worſt of
all wars; and what we have gained, the <hi>bleſſings
of Peace,</hi> and <hi>Kingly Government</hi> the beſt preſerver
of them; a gracious PRINCE, and together with
him our <hi>Laws, Liberties, Properties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> the <hi>free exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
of Religious Duties,</hi> indeed all that is or ought
to be dear to a Chriſtian Common-wealth in this
world: If we conſider I ſay what he hath removed
from us, and what he hath given to us, the <hi>Bleſſing</hi>
will appear in it <hi>ſelf</hi> wonderfull; and in its kind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
compare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115685:18"/>
3. And yet his <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Liberality</hi> in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of beſtowing it,<note place="margin">3. Of the Manner of giving it.</note> is as wonderful as the <hi>Gift</hi> it
ſelf, and more; and that in a double reſpect.
For firſt; he did it graciouſly, freely, <hi>Nullo ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedente
merito, nullo expectato commodo;</hi> he ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
in us before to move him to it; he looks
for nothing after from us for it, but onely that
we ſhould be kinde to our ſelves in a right uſe of
his benefits; that ſo we may be capable of more
and greater, which we long not ſo much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
as he to give. And</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Becauſe what he gives in <hi>frowns</hi> and
<hi>thunder</hi> to others, he hath reached out to us <hi>ſmiling,</hi>
and in his <hi>ſtill voice,</hi> what they <hi>buy</hi> by all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
of War, and think it a good purchaſe oft at
the expence of much treaſure, and a ſea of Blood,
is freely caſt upon us without more coſt or trouble
then of a few <hi>Conceſsions</hi> of a <hi>gracious Prince;</hi> now
ſo great a <hi>bleſſing</hi> at ſo eaſie a rate, ſo much for ſo
little, muſt needs highly commend his bounty,
and make the <hi>manner of his giving equal</hi> to the <hi>gift</hi> it
ſelf</p>
                  <p>4 And as the <hi>Manner moſt gracious,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4. Of the Time when.</note> ſo was the
<hi>Time</hi> too. A little thing ſeaſonably done, deſerves
much: This was great in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> gracious in the
<hi>manner,</hi> ſeaſonable for the <hi>time;</hi> 'tis danger that
makes <hi>deliverance</hi> ſweet. <hi>Placet cunctis ſecuritas, &amp;c.</hi>
ſays St <hi>Bernard,</hi> Security is pleaſing to all, but to
him moſt that feared moſt; and to be ſnatched
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115685:19"/>
out of the jaws of <hi>Death,</hi> gives a double <hi>Life.</hi>
This was our caſe; <hi>reſcued,</hi> when ready to <hi>periſh,</hi>
when <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State, Religion, Learning, Laws,</hi>
were not only in danger, but already devoured,
in the hope and expectation of our enemies; when
<hi>Atheiſm, Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Barbariſm,</hi> were in a full
and fierce torrent, breaking in upon us, and we
at the very brink of a remedileſs confuſion, ready
to be made the pity and ſcorn of the whole world,
as they ſtood affected to us; <hi>Then,</hi> even <hi>then,</hi> in
this preſſing neceſſity, at this moſt acceptable
<hi>Time,</hi> did the day begin to break, and his mercy
to ſhine upon us; then we firſt diſcerned our <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance</hi>
dawning, which, by ſeveral gracious
ſteps and degrees, he hath ſince worderfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
                  <p>5. And as at a <hi>Time</hi> moſt ſeaſonable for our
neceſſities,<note place="margin">5. Of the Perſons to whom.</note> ſo, to make the mercy on all hands
compleat, at a <hi>Time</hi> too, when we ſeemed <hi>moſt
uncapable of it,</hi> moſt <hi>unworthy of it:</hi> For who,
or what were we, that ſuch a bleſſing ſhould be
caſt upon us? not only <hi>undeſerving,</hi> but <hi>ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving,</hi>
and that in a high meaſure; moſt worthy
to be utterly <hi>conſumed,</hi> moſt unworthy to be <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved:</hi>
And you know the leſs worth in the
<hi>Receiver,</hi> ever the more favour in the <hi>Giver.</hi> But
to take a right eſteem of our ſelves, we may do wel
to conſider,</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115685:19"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. What our condition was before theſe Judgments fell
upon us.</item>
                     <item>2. What under them.</item>
                     <item>3. What at the time of our deliverance from them.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>1. At firſt,<note place="margin">1. What our condition was before our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſings</hi> we had ſo <hi>many,</hi> ſo <hi>great,</hi> as
no Nation under Heaven enjoyed <hi>more</hi> or <hi>greater:</hi>
But did we grow the better by them? were we
thankful for them? Far from it; God knows
we forgot many, undervalued more, abuſed all.
In ſtead of the fruits of ſo great a bounty, nothing
to be ſeen among us but horrid impudent ſins;
<hi>Non furtiva ſcelera ſed in publicum miſſa</hi> (as the <hi>Stoick</hi>
of his time;) not ſneaking, private, concealed
ſins, as fearing the <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>ſhame</hi> of the World;
but <hi>open, publick,</hi> and <hi>National ſins;</hi> Drunkenneſs,
Reeling in the ſtreets, Blaſphemy ſounding in the
Market-place, Perjury in Courts of Juſtice,
Churches themſelves not free, Pride and Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
Luxury and Prophaneneſs, Luſt and Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
and what not? But above all, our baſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude</hi>
amidſt the greateſt Bleſſings, ever reſtleſs
and impatient, complaining of the Times, and
murmuring at thoſe under whoſe bleſſed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
we enjoyed them with ſo great ſecurity.
Our own hearts muſt needs witneſs againſt us,
That the accuſation is moſt juſt; and 'tis not a
time to trifle with our ſelves, to palliate and exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate
our <hi>ſins,</hi> but freely and fully to confeſs them,
if we mean not to make void his preſent <hi>Mercies,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115685:20"/>
and pull yet greater <hi>Judgments</hi> upon us. This ſin
made us think our <hi>Peace</hi> a <hi>burden,</hi> and gave us no
quiet till we had thrown away thoſe ineſtimable
bleſſings; and for want of other Enemies, with
our own hands pull miſchief upon our ſelves, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
ſcourging and afflicting one another by all
the miſeries of a bloudy, civil and unnatural War:
And thus came his <hi>Judgements</hi> upon us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>And now to proceed.</head>
                  <p>2. When <hi>Gideon</hi> returned from the purſuit of
the two Kings of <hi>Midian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. What un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</note> and had <hi>torn the men of
Succoth and Penuel with the thorns and bryars of the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi>
'tis ſaid, that with them he <hi>taught the men
of Succoth,</hi> Judg. 8. 16. becauſe afflictions and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
uſe to do it, uſe to <hi>teach</hi> men <hi>Wit</hi> and
<hi>Vertue,</hi> uſe to reſtrain them from their wicked
courſes. Did our mutual <hi>tearing</hi> of one anothers
fleſh <hi>teach us?</hi> Had it ſo good an effect upon us?
Alas no: we grew not better, but worſe by it;
our <hi>ſins</hi> multiplied with, and much beyond our
<hi>ſufferings,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Atheiſm, Profaneneſſe, Sacriledge,
Perjury, Oppreſſion, innocent Blood</hi> of all Degrees,
<hi>Vulgar, Noble, Sacred</hi> and <hi>Royal;</hi> not to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
without tears of blood to bewail it.</p>
                  <p>So that when we were come to this height of
wickedneſs, and made our ſelves the reproach of
the whole world, what could we in reaſon expect,
but that the full Vials, and the very dregs of his
wrath ſhould be poured down upon us, and we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115685:20"/>
utterly deſtroyed from the face of the earth?</p>
                  <p>3. Yet ſo wonderful was his mercy,<note place="margin">3. What at the time of our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> even in
in this ſtate and condition, when our provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
reached up to Heaven, ſeemed to contend and
prevail too, both againſt his Love and Anger, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing
the one, contemning the other, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting
by neither; when thus full ripe for deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
yet, as if he were reſolved not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
by our ingratitude, nor ſuffer any thing to
hinder his gracious purpoſes towards us, he hath,
by a <hi>Miracle of Mercy,</hi> removed his Judgments
from us, and becalmed that tempeſt that lay ſo
heavy upon us, what can we do leſs then cry out
with our Prophet, <hi>O that men would therefore praiſe
the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare the wonders that
he doth for the children of men.</hi> Pſa. 107.</p>
                  <p>And now if we be not wholly drowned in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality,
if we be not guilty of a ſtupidity beyond
what humane nature ſeems capable of, we muſt
needs be highly and paſſionately ſenſible of ſo
melting, ſo ſurprizing, ſo amazing a Mercy; ſo
<hi>exceeding great</hi> in all conſiderations: So great the
<hi>Giver,</hi> ſo vile the <hi>Receivers;</hi> the <hi>Gift</hi> ſo great, the
<hi>Manner</hi> ſo kind, the <hi>Time</hi> ſo ſeaſonable, and <hi>We</hi> ſo
<hi>unworthy</hi> of it: what can be more to commend it
to us? And therefore, if we have but near that
reliſh of it in the <hi>heart</hi> as we ought, and as it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,
it will break out at the <hi>mouth,</hi> and break
out it muſt into <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving:</hi> For that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115685:21"/>
was the next part of <hi>Davids Gratitude,</hi> and muſt be
ſo of ours.</p>
                  <q>I will give thanks unto thee, O Lord, and ſing
praiſes to thy Name, among the Heathen.</q>
                  <p>2. If <hi>Gratitude</hi> be in the heart,<note place="margin">2. Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the tongue.</note> if all be right
within, ſomething will appear without: If there
be that apprehenſion, that eſtimation of the <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi>
as it deſerves, it cannot be kept there no more
then fire in the boſome, it will break out in <hi>thanks</hi>
and <hi>praiſe;</hi> the full <hi>heart</hi> will run over at the <hi>mouth,</hi>
it muſt have a vent by the <hi>tongue:</hi> And ſo indeed
it ſhould, both for our own good, and for others
too. The <hi>tongue</hi> was principally given (you
know) to ſet forth his <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> and it
concerns us to uſe it accordingly. We offend with
it as much as with any member, and therefore
ſhould by it endeavour to make ſome compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and take care it be as ſerviceable as before ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.
We pull down <hi>Judgments</hi> by it, and 'tis but
meet we give <hi>thanks</hi> with it for our <hi>Deliverance;</hi>
elſe we ſhall be found guilty of <hi>cold affections, dull
reſentments</hi> of his favours: We rob God of his <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
and others of the benefit of his <hi>Mercies</hi> to us,
for whoſe ſakes we receive them as well as for our
own; that <hi>they,</hi> as well as <hi>we,</hi> may have comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
hopes of <hi>Deliverance,</hi> when in <hi>diſtreſſe;</hi> and
learn by our example to give <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> to his
Name.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115685:21"/>
Neceſſary then it is,<note place="margin">1. Publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> that the <hi>Tongue</hi> have its
part in the diſcharge of this duty; our <hi>thanks</hi> muſt
be <hi>vocal,</hi> and more then that, they muſt be <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi>
too and <hi>diffuſive. David</hi> would not pay them
privately, and to a few, but <hi>publickly,</hi> even among
the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> and without, even to all
mankinde. He was a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and foreſaw the
converſion of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and that the <hi>Pſalm</hi> he
compoſed ſhould be ſung to the <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of
<hi>God</hi> among them, that his example ſhould mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
matter of <hi>thanks</hi> to all ſucceeding ages. But I
promiſed not to meddle with the <hi>Prophetical ſenſe</hi>
at all; the <hi>Literal</hi> reacheth far enough to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
and may ſuffice to teach us to imitate
him in publiſhing our thanks as he did, who
(that none might be ignorant of his <hi>Gratitude,</hi> who
had heard of his <hi>Deliverance)</hi> would do it in <hi>the great
Congregation,</hi> and among much people, <hi>Pſal</hi> 35. 18.
He calls to others to aſſiſt him, and joyn with
him; to do it themſelves, <hi>Tell the people what things
he hath done.</hi> Pſal. 105. 1. <hi>O come hither and hearken,
and I will tell you what he hath done for my Soul.</hi> Pſal.
66. 16. And, <hi>O praiſe the Lord with me, and let us
magnifie his name together.</hi> Pſal. 34 3. <hi>O be joyful all
the Lands;</hi> and many ſuch like. He will do it to
every body, that all may praiſe God as well as he;
he will not be aſhamed, nor ſhould we, to own
and confeſſe, and acknowledge, and publiſh his
bounty in all places, and before all perſons, as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115685:22"/>
occaſion and opportunity is offered. A heart truly
affected with a ſenſe, and due eſteem of his mercy,
will do it, cannot forbear to do it, is reſtleſs till
it have done it. Both <hi>publickly</hi> and <hi>chearfully</hi> too,
another circumſtance in the manner of giving our
<hi>thanks;</hi> of which likewiſe,</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Prophet</hi> gives here an example,<note place="margin">2. chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</note> for he will
not onely ſay, but <hi>Sing praiſes unto his Name;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
a <hi>joyfulneſs</hi> as well as <hi>thankfulneſs.</hi> And ſo it
ſhould be, and ſo it muſt be. For as to <hi>Feaſt</hi> when
God calls to <hi>Faſt;</hi> to <hi>ſing,</hi> when he calls to <hi>ſigh,</hi>
is in the Prophet, <hi>an iniquity not eaſily purged, Iſai.</hi>
22. 12, 13, 14. (To frolick it under his <hi>judgments,</hi>
and to deſpiſe them ſo much, as not to ſeem ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
of them, is a great <hi>ſin,</hi> and I fear no ſmall part
of our former guilt.) So, on the contrary, to carry
<hi>ſour countenances</hi> vvhen his <hi>ſhines</hi> upon us, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
his mercies vvith a ſullen and ſad heart, an
unfeeling diſpoſition, or but vvith an indifferency;
not to be at all tranſported, at all moved vvith
them, is a <hi>ſin</hi> that deſerves a deſertion, a recalling
of his <hi>favors,</hi> a doubling his <hi>judgments</hi> upon us.
A ſad example vve have in the people of God.
<hi>Deut. 28. 47, 48. Becauſe thou didſt not ſerve the Lord
thy God with joyfulneſs, and with gladneſs of heart, for
the abundance of all things: Therefore thou ſhalt ſerve
thine enemies in hunger, thirſt, and nakedneſs, and in the
want of all things.</hi> An heavy doom, and the reaſon of
it is; vvhere there is no <hi>joy without,</hi> there can be no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115685:22"/>
                     <hi>hearty thanks within.</hi> For how can we eſteem any
thing <hi>a bleſſing</hi> that <hi>delights</hi> us not? And how are
we delighted if we ſhew no ſigns of <hi>joy</hi> for it?
And how does he value a Deliverance, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes
no comfort he takes in it? This is certainly
a great ſin, an high provocation of God. What
ſhall we ſay then to thoſe ſowre and over-leaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
natures, that with the ſame countenance keep a
<hi>Faſt</hi> and a <hi>Feſtival,</hi> a day of <hi>Humiliation</hi> and <hi>Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,</hi>
both alike, with ſighs, and groans, and
caſt down looks; as if <hi>griefs</hi> and <hi>groans</hi> were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
ſign of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> when the <hi>Devils</hi>
howl and are tormented.</p>
                  <p>But I would not be mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aken; 'tis not a <hi>profane
rejoycing,</hi> a ſinful mirth we plead for; far be it
from us: How much thoſe uſual expreſſions of
jollity, <hi>ſinging, feaſting,</hi> and the like, are abuſed
to Luxury and Riot, Exceſs and Wantonneſs,
<hi>Novimus &amp; Dolemus,</hi> (as the Father) we know
it, we grieve for it, we deteſt it as much as any.
An horrid ſin it is, in ſtead of <hi>thanking God,</hi> to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
to <hi>Bacchus;</hi> to expreſs <hi>Publicum gaudium per
Publicum dedecus,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> of the Heathen:
That's to pay <hi>thanks</hi> with <hi>unthankfulneſſe,</hi> to make
<hi>Mercy</hi> the Mother of <hi>Sin,</hi> to return evil for good,
the worſt, the higheſt, the baſeſt <hi>Ingratitude.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>corruption</hi> of the <hi>beſt</hi> things is ever the <hi>worſt,</hi>
and what's moſt <hi>neceſſary</hi> in the <hi>uſe,</hi> is ever moſt
<hi>dangerous</hi> in the <hi>abuſe:</hi> And ſo 'tis here; abuſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115685:23"/>
                     <hi>Mirth</hi> and nothing worſe, uſe it right and nothing
better; keep it within its bounds, ſuffer it not to
tranſport us beyond our duty into ſin, and 'tis the
<hi>Balm of this Life,</hi> the <hi>Earneſt of a better,</hi> the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and ſeaſoning, that which makes pleaſant
all actions Moral and Religious.</p>
                  <p>'Tis an excellent Rule of Life St. <hi>Bernard</hi> gives,
<hi>Do well, and be merry;</hi> as merry as you will, the
more the better; keep to the firſt, you cannot
offend in the ſecond. And let me tell you, that
<hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> are the moſt <hi>chearfull</hi> things in
the World, however ſome make them ſowr and
ſevere; they are, like God himſelf, all light and
ſerenity, joy and comf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt, eſpecially in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
                  <p>God loves the chearful Servant, and who does
not? We may judge it by our ſelves. Who cares
for him that goes to his <hi>work</hi> as if he went to the
<hi>Stocks</hi> or a <hi>Priſon?</hi> All parts of Gods ſervice, even
the ſowreſt and ſevereſt (had we time to ſhew it)
are mixed with comforts, and ſhould be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
joyfully; this of <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond,
and more then any: For here we ſwim
with the ſtream. We are naturally chearful after
a miſchief avoided, a danger eſcaped; and being
ſo well prepared for it, ſhould with all alacrity
<hi>ſing</hi> out our <hi>thanks</hi> and his <hi>praiſe,</hi> declare an exulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of mind in all innocent and decent expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of joy and gladneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115685:23"/>
'Twas ever the cuſtome of all mankind to do
it, in all Ages and places: Inſtances are infinite
both within the Church and without. But in
this haſt we need go no further then the Prophet
<hi>David,</hi> who in the Book of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> for his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
deliverances, is ever at <hi>[I will ſing,]</hi> or <hi>[O ſing
unto the Lord:]</hi> either doing it himſelf, or calling
others to do it, not coldly or faintly, but zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and heartily; <hi>Sing aloud, make a chearfull noiſe;
Sing luſtily unto him with a good courage.</hi> But this
will not ſerve the turn neither, unleſs he call for
Inſtruments, as well as men to aſſiſt; <hi>Bring hither
the Tabret, the merry Harp, and the Lute, blow the
Trumpet too,</hi> all to incite quicken and enflame his
heart and affections, even to a tranſporting exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
joy of gratitude.</p>
                  <p>We ſhould indeed labour to foment it in us as
much as may be, for the greater <hi>joy without,</hi> the
greater <hi>ſenſe</hi> and eſteem of his <hi>bounty within;</hi> and
the greater that is, ever the more, and the more
ſincere <hi>Gratitude;</hi> which if it be not <hi>heard</hi> in our
<hi>Tongues,</hi> is certainly not <hi>felt</hi> in our <hi>Hearts,</hi> and
therefore there it muſt be alſo.</p>
                  <p>And when this is done, the ſecond part of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
is performed; the <hi>Tongue</hi> hath done her
part, but all is not yet done; this is but <hi>Gratiarum
dictio,</hi> it reacheth no further then <hi>words,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
muſt be <hi>done</hi> as well as <hi>ſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115685:24"/>
The <hi>thanks</hi> of ſome are vocal enough,<note place="margin">3. Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in the hand.</note> too
much, becauſe nothing elſe, nothing but ſound
and noiſe; and better a dumb heart then not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.
Words are a cheap way of payment, and
the world delights much in it; Gods benefits are
not <hi>words,</hi> but <hi>deeds,</hi> and our Gratitude will be
found ſhort if it reach not beyond words to <hi>deeds.</hi>
Nay, Honeſty and Reaſon require, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation
exceed the benefit received, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
be made both in greater <hi>meaſure,</hi> and with
greater alacrity (if it may be;) Becauſe he that
gave was, <hi>not obliged,</hi> he that returns, is; the one
comes from a free and liberal <hi>mind,</hi> the other is a
piece of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and a Debt: And though we
have paid what's due to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> in returning as
much as we received; yet we are not upon even
terms, unleſs we ſuffer one <hi>kindneſſe</hi> to beget an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
and return ſomething over and above, and
more then we received. A good man will do it
when he can, and have a good mind, an earneſt
<hi>deſire</hi> to do it when he cannot. And ſo ſhould
we to God, ſince 'tis impoſſible to make him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
returns in <hi>fact,</hi> we muſt do it <hi>in voto,</hi> in
deſire. And though neither our <hi>deeds</hi> nor <hi>deſires</hi>
can in any degree equal his Bounty, but we muſt
needs fall infinitely ſhort in both; yet if we do
what we can, and heartily wiſh we could do
more, 'tis accepted with him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115685:24"/>
And <hi>ſomething</hi> (ſure) we can do, and that <hi>ſomething</hi>
we muſt do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now to learn what it is, we muſt
conſider; why we were <hi>afflicted,</hi> and why <hi>deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
afflicted we were for our <hi>ſins,</hi> delivered that
we might <hi>ſin no more.</hi> What thoſe <hi>ſins</hi> were that
pulled down his <hi>judgments</hi> upon us, you heard
before; how many, how great, how publick,
how bold and daring; how our <hi>provocations</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed
with and beyond his <hi>judgments.</hi> And
now being delivered, we muſt remember, that
<hi>mercy</hi> is ever ſhewed <hi>propter ſpem,</hi> in hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment;
and therefore take care to avoid thoſe
ſins hereafter; at leaſt to be ſure to prevent their
being publick and national any more. For if
inſtead of improving this bleſſing of <hi>Peace</hi> to
his glory, the good of others, and of our ſelves,
we abuſe it to pride and vanities, pleaſure and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality,
exceſs and riot, we may be aſſured it will
prove no bleſſing at all, but an <hi>aggravation,</hi> both of
our <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>miſery,</hi> in bringing a worſe War,
and heavier judgments upon us, then we have
yet felt.</p>
                  <p>But this is not all,<note place="margin">2. In doing good.</note> we have more to do, to be
thankful as we ſhould, then this; then barely to
<hi>avoid ſin;</hi> we muſt <hi>do good</hi> too. For the general
end of all his bleſſings upon us, his mercies to us,
and <hi>deliverance</hi> of us, of what kinde ſoever, is to
lead us to a <hi>holy, vertuous,</hi> and <hi>religious life,</hi> St. <hi>Luk.</hi>
1. 74, 75. We are brought into danger and diſtreſs,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115685:25"/>
becauſe <hi>bad,</hi> delivered that we may be <hi>better.</hi> And
this is the right <hi>giving of thanks,</hi> the beſt return we
can make him, and the beſt eſteemed by him:
And ſo (you ſee) there is much more required to
make up this duty, then <hi>words;</hi> much before, and
much after, the <hi>heart</hi> before, and after the <hi>hands.</hi>
If the firſt (the <hi>heart)</hi> be wanting, <hi>words</hi> are but
<hi>wind,</hi> not better, nor ſo innocent as the pratling
of a Parrat. <hi>Gratitude</hi> is <hi>heartleſs</hi> without the one,
and <hi>lame</hi> without the other. When either is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
(the <hi>heart</hi> or <hi>hands)</hi> the <hi>Tongue</hi> is an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi>
and gives <hi>lies</hi> inſtead of <hi>thanks;</hi> real thanks are
good deeds, and they praiſe him beſt, that obey
him beſt.</p>
                  <p>But now among thoſe many duties a good life
comprehends,<note place="margin">1. By gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</note> and we in <hi>gratitude</hi> are obliged
unto; ſome are more ſeaſonable, more proper for
this time and occaſion. And to make the choice,
we ſhall eſpecially conſider, that as <hi>God hath done
great things for us,</hi> ſo it is neceſſary we <hi>do ſomething</hi>
again for him: As he hath <hi>given</hi> to us, ſo we <hi>to
give</hi> to him. Alas, how can that be! ſince our
goods reach not to him, <hi>he</hi> needs them not. True
indeed, but <hi>His</hi> do; the <hi>poor</hi> need, and by them
our goods reach even to <hi>Him</hi> too. We relieve him
in the <hi>poor,</hi> viſit him in the <hi>ſick,</hi> cloath him in the
<hi>naked,</hi> redeem him in the <hi>priſoner: For in that we do
it to theſe, we do it to him, Matth.</hi> 25. 45. And no time
more ſeaſonable to do it in, none fitter then this:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115685:25"/>
That at a <hi>publick rejoycing</hi> none may be <hi>ſad,</hi> nor <hi>faſt</hi>
when others <hi>feaſt:</hi> And therefore, being cheered,
refreſhed, and comforted our ſelves, let us cheer,
refreſh, and comfort others; and being delivered
our ſelves, let's deliver others from diſtreſs and
want; thoſe eſpecially that have ſuffered in the
late diſturbances, the <hi>ſick,</hi> the <hi>maimed,</hi> the <hi>lame,</hi> the
<hi>deſolate Widows</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> of ſuch as fell in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
Let's be ſure to make them (as well as our
ſelves) ſenſible of <hi>Gods favors</hi> to us: Let the <hi>bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi>
of <hi>peace</hi> diſtil from the <hi>head</hi> to the <hi>skirts,</hi> to the
very meaneſt among us: <hi>Works of Charity</hi> are a
proper <hi>ſacrifice</hi> of <hi>thankſgiving</hi> at ſuch a time as
this.</p>
                  <p>But beſides <hi>giving,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</note> there muſt be <hi>forgiving</hi> too,
a duty at this time as ſeaſonable as the other, if
not more; for it is the beſt part of our <hi>Gratitude</hi>
to <hi>God,</hi> and the moſt acceptable to him, and we
ſhall be without excuſe, if we do it not. For
ſhall God forgive us <hi>Thouſands of Talents<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſins many
in number, great in weight? And ſhall we ſtick
at a <hi>few pence,</hi> a few petty injuries of our Brethren,
neither great, nor many; but ſuch as for <hi>number</hi>
or <hi>weight</hi> can ſtand in no compariſon with ours
againſt him? Shall <hi>God,</hi> ſo great, ſo glorious, after
ſo high and many provocations, condeſcend to
be at peace with us, and give us an aſſurance of
it, by removing his <hi>judgments,</hi> and <hi>crowning</hi> us
with many <hi>bleſſings?</hi> And ſhall <hi>we</hi> (poor worms)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115685:26"/>
be at enmity among our ſelves for trifles, and that
to the hazard of all the <hi>comforts</hi> of this life, and
hopes of a better? Shall <hi>we</hi> retain the memory of
former unkindneſſes, and make a <hi>Publick Act of
Oblivion,</hi> which we expect a <hi>publick lye;</hi> without
either fear of <hi>God,</hi> or ſhame of the <hi>World?</hi> This is
not to <hi>have peace,</hi> or enjoy it; but with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude
to <hi>throw</hi> it at him again; it is but to
change one war into another, the open into ſecret,
hoſtility into treachery; and, by pretending <hi>peace</hi>
and <hi>kindneſs,</hi> to ſmooth the way to <hi>ſupplantation</hi> and
<hi>injury,</hi> the moſt <hi>baſe, ſerpentine, unmanly thing</hi> in the
World.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I beſeech you, take care that we<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
ſtrip our ſelves of all <hi>unruly paſſions,</hi> that we may
have <hi>peace within,</hi> peace from turbulent, revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
affections: For unleſs we have this, what's
<hi>outward peace</hi> worth? Certainly no more to thee
then health in the <hi>City,</hi> when the <hi>Plague</hi> is in thy
<hi>boſome.</hi> Let's all ſeriouſly and ſadly look back,
conſider, and bemoan one another: For what we
have mutually done and ſuffered from each other;
let's all be <hi>ſorry</hi> for it, and all <hi>mend,</hi> perfectly <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi>
what's paſt, and returning to as great a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
as ever, and a greater then ever; that ſo, by all
<hi>mutual good Offices</hi> we may make amends for our
former <hi>Animoſities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It hath been our cuſtom indeed (and more
ſhame for us) to <hi>forget benefits,</hi> to write them in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115685:26"/>
                     <hi>ſand,</hi> but injuries in <hi>marble;</hi> we muſt now invert
the order, write <hi>Gods benefits</hi> in marble, others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries
in ſand, if we write them at all; never <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get</hi>
the one, never <hi>remember</hi> the other; that's the
beſt, the moſt <hi>Chriſtian memory,</hi> which (as <hi>Caeſars)
forgets</hi> nothing but <hi>injuries:</hi> We ſhould all do it,
and <hi>Princes</hi> above all; for it becomes a <hi>Publick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
to look upon all as <hi>ſons,</hi> upon the <hi>Prodigals,</hi>
with more kindneſs and tenderneſs, when they
once come to themſelves, acknowledge their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,
when he ſees them <hi>returning,</hi> though <hi>afar off,</hi>
to <hi>run,</hi> and <hi>meet,</hi> and <hi>careſs</hi> them; to call for the
<hi>Ring</hi> and the <hi>Robe;</hi> to ſet ſome marks of favour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them more then ordinary, that may give aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
to the World and them, that the promiſes
made them, were not the <hi>effects of neceſsity,</hi> but the
<hi>fruits</hi> of a <hi>gracious Princely minde,</hi> inviolably reſolved
to outdo all his <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Engagements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">3. By per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering in both.</note> and to conclude, Let every one of us
(I beſeech you) think upon theſe and the like du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
which this time and occaſion call for, and
continue them at all times. <hi>Gratitude</hi> is not the
buſineſs of a day or year, but of our <hi>whole life.
Benefits</hi> new and freſh, are uſually entertained by
us with <hi>warm affections,</hi> but (more ſhame for us)
a little time cools them, deads them: And <hi>dangers</hi>
are too oft at once paſt and forgotten; or if we
ſet apart a time, a <hi>Day of Thankſgiving</hi> (as now we
do) when that is paſt, commonly our thanks paſs
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115685:27"/>
with it, and we return to our old vanities again.
<hi>David</hi> does not ſo, he gives a better example; he
ſays, <hi>I will give thanks,</hi> I will <hi>begin,</hi> (and indeed he
had begun before he ſaid it) but he ſays not
when he will <hi>end,</hi> he ſets no time for that; nor
could he, becauſe it ſhould have none, it ſhould
be without end: And therefore elſewhere
he is at it; <hi>Every day will I give thanks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
thee, and praiſe thy Name for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi>
Pſal. 145. 2. 'Tis <hi>undecent,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<hi>unjuſt,</hi> our <hi>Thanks</hi> ſhould be <hi>tranſitory,</hi> when
the <hi>Benefit</hi> is <hi>laſting.</hi> Now that, (if we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
it not by unthankfulneſs) laſts as long as wee;
we are, and ever ſhall be, the better for it; For had
we periſhed in the danger, we had utterly loſt the
benefit of this and all ſucceeding Mercies. Our
<hi>Thanks</hi> then ſhould laſt as long as it laſts, and that's
as long as we laſt, and muſt not end before us.
and therefore let every one of us, as we are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
take up <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution and practiſe, and
ſay with him, <hi>Praiſe the Lord, O my ſoul; while I
live will I praiſe the Lord, as long as I have any being will
I ſing praiſe unto my God.</hi> Pſal. 146. 1. And thus <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
and thus <hi>doing,</hi> we ſhall continue thoſe Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings
upon us, which may make this and ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Generations happy. Which God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
